<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc-ext allow-markup-in-artwork="yes" ?>
<!--<?rfc-ext refresh-from="draft-reschke-http-jfv-latest.xml" ?>-->

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY mdash "&#8212;">
  <!ENTITY Note "<x:h xmlns:x='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>Note:</x:h>">
  <!ENTITY MAY "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>MAY</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY MUST "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>MUST</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY MUST-NOT "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>MUST NOT</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY OPTIONAL "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>OPTIONAL</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY RECOMMENDED "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY REQUIRED "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>REQUIRED</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY SHALL "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>SHALL</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY SHALL-NOT "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>SHALL NOT</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY SHOULD "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>SHOULD</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY SHOULD-NOT "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>">
]>
<rfc xmlns:x="http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext" xmlns:ed="http://greenbytes.de/2002/rfcedit" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-reschke-objsec-latest" category="std" xml:lang="en" x:maturity-level="informational">

  <!--<x:feedback template="mailto:ietf-http-wg@w3.org?subject={docname},%20%22{section}%22&amp;body=&lt;{ref}&gt;:"/>-->

	<front>
  <title abbrev="fine-grained end-to-end">A rationale for fine-grained intermediary-aware end-to-end protocols</title>
  <author initials="D." surname="Druta" fullname="Dan Druta">
    <organization>AT&amp;T</organization>
    <address>
      <email>dd5826@att.com</email>	
    </address>
  </author>
  <author initials="T." surname="Fossati" fullname="Thomas Fossati">
    <organization>Alcatel-Lucent</organization>
    <address>
      <email>thomas.fossati@alcatel-lucent.com</email>	
    </address>
  </author>
  <author initials="M." surname="Ihlar" fullname="Marcus Ihlar">
    <organization>Ericsson</organization>
    <address>
      <email>marcus.ihlar@ericsson.com</email>	
    </address>
  </author>
  <author initials="G." surname="Klas" fullname="Guenter Klas">
    <organization>Vodafone</organization>
    <address>
      <email>Guenter.Klas@vodafone.com</email>	
    </address>
  </author>
  <author initials="D. R." surname="Lopez" fullname="Diego R. Lopez">
    <organization>Telefonica I+D</organization>
    <address>
      <email>diego.r.lopez@telefonica.com</email>	
    </address>
  </author>
  <author initials="J. F." surname="Reschke" fullname="Julian F. Reschke" role="editor">
    <organization abbrev="greenbytes">greenbytes GmbH</organization>
    <address>
      <email>julian.reschke@greenbytes.de</email>	
    </address>
  </author>

  <date year="2014"/>
  
  <abstract>
    <t>
    </t>
  </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>

<section title="Introduction" anchor="introduction">
<t>
  In the last decade, the generalization of network access, the cloud and the
  ubiquity of the Web as an application platform has translated into an
  unprecedented increase in the use of the Internet, facilitated by the
  development of new web standards and the innovations in mobile technologies.
  With this growth in use, there has been an increased amount of personal data
  being sent over multi hop public links.
</t>
<t>
  In order to protect the integrity and confidentiality of the online
  transactions, http traffic can be secured with transport layer security using
  https. While https is great for e-commerce and banking and while there is a
  sense of understanding in the user community around the secure nature of
  https, using TLS and https for the majority of the traffic has performance
  and functional drawbacks, mainly because the http session is encrypted as a
  whole.
</t>
<t>
  Looking from the privacy and security perspective, it is clear that users
  must be aware if and when an intermediary node is intercepting their traffic
  and they have the right to continue or demand higher levels of privacy by
  encrypting what they deem to be sensitive information. The privacy threshold
  depends on user's tolerance and the trust they put in the intermediary's
  reputation, as well as whether the user is the ultimate consent authority
  for a given connection: for example a parent or employer may take that role
  for a connection used by a child or employee.
</t>
<t>
  Modern web architecture involves sophisticated caching schemes that involve
  fetching various objects (images, libraries, etc.) from various locations in
  the path to avoid latency and improve the overall user experience while
  reducing bandwidth use. This is an important aspect especially in the
  developing countries, remote locations and in general areas that lack fast
  network infrastructure.
</t>
<t>
  Issues thus arise from the clash of two trends: One is towards enhanced
  privacy calling for integrity, confidentiality and anonymity. The other one
  is towards improved performance and lower latency, calling for caching,
  compression, and adaptability.
</t>
<t>
  This is also reflected in the views of important stakeholders. Users want to
  make informed decisions in regards to whom they trust with their data. They
  also want to have control over what data they share with whom.
</t>
<t>
  Web site owners and content providers on the other hand are keen to get the
  most cost efficient and reliable way to deliver information and services to
  their users and customers, while preserving their confidentiality, protecting
  their privacy and the integrity of their data.
</t>
<t>
  As different entities seek to meet the requirements of their stakeholders,
  they sometimes apply solutions which generate conflicts. Clients act on
  behalf of end users and solutions may include local caches and browser
  proxies. Servers act on behalf of content providers and solutions may include
  the use of CDNs and reverse proxies. Intermediaries operated by communication
  service providers and network operators act on behalf of users and/or content
  providers and solutions include means for access network optimization and
  content filtering.
</t>
<t>
  In above context, the use of TLS and https looks like a "black and white
  approach", or an "all or nothing" approach which doesn't lend itself to
  resolving above-mentioned conflicts. The question arises: Can "color be added"?
</t>
<t>
  TLS is a client server protocol and it serves its purpose perfectly in many
  client-server scenarios and use cases. But then the web has evolved to become
  a mesh. Average traffic flows now involve various intermediaries between
  clients and servers. They add value by performing different functions
  including multiple levels of optimization.
</t>
<t>
  The application of TLS forces point-to-point flows which cuts out
  intermediaries and can lead to significant drawbacks. It reduces e.g. the
  optimization options which translates into increasing traffic volumes in
  access networks, higher latency and overall decreasing quality of experience
  for users.
</t>
<t>
  It can be observed that ignoring the role of intermediaries on the Internet
  does not necessarily make the Internet more secure. In fact, in some cases it
  forces various parties to break the TLS promise of e2e integrity and
  confidentiality in order to meet their legal obligations (enterprises).
</t>
<t>
  We suggest the solution to the challenge lies in "adding color". An example
  of this are fine-grained intermediary-aware end-to-end protocols. 
</t>
<t>
  Assuming the existence of such a fine-grained protocol, the following
  benefits could be imagined which leads to satisfying the justified needs
  of multiple stakeholders:
</t>
<t> 
  The ability to atomically encrypt objects or even http frames should support
  this sophisticated caching mechanisms while allowing content providers to
  avoid distributing their server key material across the network nodes and
  prevent the risk of compromising their security.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Objectives">
<t>
  Given the short description of the problem above, the following objectives can be derived.
</t>
<t><list style="numbers">
  <t>To improve security and user-controlled privacy.</t>
  <t>To minimize passive interception and man in the middle attacks.</t>
  <t>To allow the client (user) and the server (content provider) to negotiate what and whom they want to give (or not) visibility into their traffic flows.</t>
  <t>To enable multiple levels of optimization that don't conflict with each other and either meet all parties expectations or maximise the benefit to as many involved parties as possible.</t>
</list></t>
<t>
  In a world of TLS and https only, it is difficult to achieve in particular objectives 3. and 4.
</t>
<t>
  The challenge therefore is in finding mechanisms or protocols which meet objectives 1. and 2. (e.g. in the way TLS is delivering against those objectives) AND simultaneously provide the added flexibility to leverage the services of 3rd party intermediaries located between client and origin server.
</t>
</section>


<section title="Benefits for the content provider, for the users, for the intermediaries">
<t>
  An object security approach will allow the different parties to establis
  end-to-end and hop-by-hop security mechanisms to different data and metadata
  elements, and therefore address what can be seen as conflicting requirements
  in terms of optimization and security capabilitites.
</t>
<t>  
The following benefits will arise for the different stakeholders:
</t>
<t>
Content providers:
<list style="symbols">
<t>Can select the type of security service that is optimal and sufficient for particular types of content: e.g. confidentiality, integrity protection, entity authentication etc.</t> 
<t>Can select which parts of their content shall be secured or not and how content shall be securely retrievable.</t>
<t>Can increase their confidence in secure temporary content storage during delivery through encrypting/signing sensitive content objects.</t>
<t>Can leverage the business services of 3rd parties (intermediaries) through enabling the intermediaries to perform value-added services. Content providers may outsource particular tasks (like caching, or offering higher security level to users) to intermediaries.</t>
<t>When using the services of content delivery networks can benefit from faster, optimised delivery over the "last mile" (as seen from the perspective of a content delivery network). Content delivery networks can optimise delivery on behalf of content providers over the first and middle mile, however they often rely on other ISPs and mobile network operators to deliver content over the last mile. Intermediaries in the last mile can optimise traffic engineering.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
Users:
<list style="symbols">
<t>Are able to enjoy sufficient privacy and security as dictated by different use cases and equally their personal preferences (e.g. protection from traffic analysis, integrity of content).</t>
<t>Can benefit from value-added services delivered by intermediaries on behalf of content providers.</t>
<t>Can have access to services offered by intermediaries which enhance end user quality of experience (e.g. malware detection, parental controls).</t>
<t>Can access web resources and services with lower latency and better response times (e.g. through intermediaries performing video pacing or traffic engineering to avoid congestion on particular networks).</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
Intermediaries:
<list style="symbols">
<t>Can play their specific roles in content delivery and communication on behalf of content providers, like 
<list style="symbols">
<t>Caching of content on behalf of content providers</t>
<t>Optimisation of content for optimal delivery on behalf of content providers</t>
<t>Video pacing on behalf of content providers.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>Can provide value-added services on behalf of users like URL filtering , parental control, malware detection etc.</t>
<t>Can optimise content delivery and data communication within a network they are associated with or control e.g. through traffic engineering and traffic management by taking into account the inherent needs of content types and the explicit real- and non-real-time requirements of content providers and content delivery networks. Thereby, intermediaries contribute to an improved "end-to-end" user experience in the interest of both users and content providers.
<list style="symbols">
<t>Intermediaries are enabled to perform congestion management and can therefore reduce latency and response times.</t>
</list></t>
<t>Can meet regulatory requirements as they may prevail in particular jurisdictions through an approach which is more open and transparent to both users and content providers, and which may be in the national interest.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section title="Analysis of related work">
<t>
  The concept of object security is not something new, several approaches targeted at different application areas exist today.
</t>
<section title="JOSE">
<t>
  JOSE stands for "JSON Object Signing and Encryption". It is a series of standards produced by the IETF under the JOSE charter (<eref target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/wg/jose/charter/"/>).
</t>
</section>
</section>

  </middle>
  <back>

  </back>

</rfc>
